<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A rumor of warres among the times and signes of peace A sermon preached at Hamsted, in Middlesex, the 6. of September 1608. By William Bailey.</title>
            <author>Bailey, William, of Stapleford Abbat, Essex.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01869</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117269</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852484</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17808</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01869)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17808)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1226:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A rumor of warres among the times and signes of peace A sermon preached at Hamsted, in Middlesex, the 6. of September 1608. By William Bailey.</title>
                  <author>Bailey, William, of Stapleford Abbat, Essex.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[58] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. E[ld] for Ed: Blount, and William Barret,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1608]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁶ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 1201a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Rumor of warres <hi>among the times and</hi> ſignes of peace.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at <hi>Hamſted,</hi> in Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex, the 6. of September 1608.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Bailey.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 37.37.</bibl> Marke the vpright man, and behold the iuſt; for the end of that man is peace.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>G. E.</hi> for <hi>Ed. Blount, and</hi> William Barret.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:2"/>
            <head>To the truly religious, and moſt vertuous Lady, the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ANNE WAADE, <hi>wife to the Right-worſhipfull, wiſe and learned,</hi> Sir WILLIAM WAADE Knight, Lieutenant to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, in his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Tower of London: grace, mercy, and peace, from God our Father, and from our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME.</hi> The Princely Prophet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Pſalmes, of the proſperitie and peace of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men. He ſet his eyes vpon their outward welfare, but conſidered not their wofull caſe, their inward feares and torments; vntill he
<pb facs="tcp:17808:3"/>went into the Sanctuarie of God, and then hee vnderſtood the eſtate, and end of ſuch men, to be wretched and miſerable. And ſurely, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer a ſenſleſſe ſecuritie, and dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (by the iust iudgment of God, blinding their eyes, and hardning their hearts) ouer-layeth and ſmoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth them, as the Harlot her Child. <hi>1. King. 3. chapter,</hi> ſo that they remaine (as it were) ſtarke dead, without any pricke of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, eating and drinking, dancing and ſinging, laughing and ſporting, as that lewd Generation immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie before the flood;
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.12.</note> yet their reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing is onely in the face (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh) not in the Heart, and their conſcience ſhall barke, (at far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt) in the vnwelcome day of their death, when the remembrance of their licentious and wicked life
<pb facs="tcp:17808:3"/>paſt, ſhall ſting them like a Scorpion. Well therefore may the iudgement of the conſcience for a while, bee ſuſpended, but it can neuer be
<note n="*" place="margin">Semper vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines furiae.</note> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; and well may wicked men, by their countenance, credit, and authoritie, eſcape the hands of man in this life, but they can neuer bee freed from the feare of the wrath of God, that ſhall ſeaze vpon them in the life to come. It is good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that euery man (while it is to day) ſeeke out, and prouide for his ſafetie and beſt eſtate: for hee is like to haue an ill day of it, that tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp armes againſt God. There is no wiſe man, going about to make <hi>warre againſt a King</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>that ſitteth not firſt downe, and taketh counſell whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee bee able with ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, to meete him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb facs="tcp:17808:4"/>againſt him with twentie thouſand.</hi> If a man could muſter all his ſinnes, and ſet downe the number of them, they would a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount indeed to very many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, but here's the miſchiefe, they are all ſuſpected and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted Souldiers, and euen Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Policie requires, that they bee diſmiſſed, and diſcharged the field, and for his vertues, they are ſo few, and ſo inſufficient, that they ſhall neuer dare to abide the brunt: there remaines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vnto him onely this, that while this reuenging GOD is yet a farre off, hee ſend an Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, and deſire conditions of peace.</p>
            <p>Some-thing <hi>(MADAME)</hi> I haue deliuered in this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, to this purpoſe. I must not
<pb facs="tcp:17808:4"/>here enlarge it, least I bee ſayd, to paſſe the nature, and exceed the meaſure of an Epiſtle. What euer it bee, I humbly preſent it to your good Ladyſhip, as an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of my hounden dutie, and ſeruice vnto Maiſter Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and your ſelfe. The Lord recompence your carefull reſpect of my weake eſtate, with eternall bleſsings: for I may ſay of you, as the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiphorus;
<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.16.</note> You haue beene a continuall refreſhing vnto mee,</hi> ſince the time of my great diſtreſſe, and exile (as I may ſpeake) from the
<note n="*" place="margin">Stapleford Abbat in Eſſex</note> Place and People of my wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes and deſires. I preached this Sermon (as your Ladyſhip may vnderſtand) at the Baptizing of your younger Sonne Maiſter <hi>IEAMES,</hi> vppon whome
<pb facs="tcp:17808:5"/>it pleaſed the Kings Maieſtie, to beſtow his owne name, that it might alwayes remaine, as an vndoubted token and pledge of his gracious fauour vnto you both, and as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse vnto your Sonne for after times, that his princely will and pleaſure is, (if he ſhall carry and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe as is fitte for the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne of ſo learned, gratious, wiſe, and valerous a Prince) to aduance him to ſuch places of dignity, as ſhall ſerue both for the exerciſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of his vertues, as alſo for the reward of their deſeruings. And now I beſeech the God of mercy, for euer to regard you and all your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (Branches of excellent hopes) with the eyes of his tender mercy &amp; compaſsion, that the ſignes of his vnſpeakeable loue and kindneſſe, may alwayes rest vpon your ſoules
<pb facs="tcp:17808:5"/>and bodies in this life, to aſſure you more and more of that most bleſſed, glorious, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talleſtate, in the life to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lady ſhips moſt affected, and moſt humbly deuoted in all dutie and ſeruice: WILLIAM BAILEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:6"/>
            <head>A Rumor of warres among the times, and ſignes of peace.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH. 48.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>There is no peace, ſaieth the Lord, vnto the wicked.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey that weare ſoft clothing,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Math. 11.8.</note> (ſaith our Sauiour) <hi>are in Kings houſes, Et mollibus veſtiuntur</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory) qui adulationibus &amp; làudibus delectantur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gre: magnus.</note> they are ſoftly clothed that loue to bee flattered and commended: I am not this prophet, nor the ſonne of this Prophet, if he haue not well ſayd, hee is old enough, let him anſwer for him-ſelfe. Surely a bold Gloſſe it is, but
<pb facs="tcp:17808:7"/>hee was a great man, and an aged, therefore for once, let him goe. But
<note n="b" place="margin">Amos. 7.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>oh thou Seer, goe farre enough, into the land of Iudah, and Propheſie there,</hi> if thou wilt, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie no more at Bethel,</hi> thou wert beſt. Alas what a miſerie were this, if I ſhould finde it thus? for
<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 15.10.</note> 
               <hi>woe is mee my Mother, thou haſt borne mee a contentious man,</hi> that cannot flatter.</p>
            <p>The Lord indeed
<note n="d" place="margin">Iſai. 57.19.</note> 
               <hi>createth the fruit of the lippes to bee peace:</hi> but ſhall I
<note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>heale the hurt of Gods people with ſweete words,</hi> and ſay, <hi>Peace, peace, when there is no peace?</hi> God forbid! If
<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> thou doe well, there is pardon, and a peaceable acceptance; but if wickedly, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not thy ſelfe with the name of peace, for <hi>there is no peace ſaith the Lord vnto the wicked.</hi> I haue digged deepe, and layed my
<pb facs="tcp:17808:7"/>foundation vppon this Rocke, (GOD bleſſe and proſper the reſt of the building:) and thus (Right Honorable) yee ſhall finde it written in the eight and fortith Chapter of the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie of <hi>Iſay,</hi> and the laſt verſe.</p>
            <q>There is no peace, ſaith the Lord, vnto the wicked.</q>
            <p>When the Arke of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord, came into the Hoſte of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the people
<note n="g" place="margin">1. Sam. 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſhou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a mighty ſhoute, ſo that the earth rang againe,</hi> and yet for all that, <hi>there fell of Iſraell</hi> by the ſword of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Philiſtins thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand footmen,</hi> in that battaile. The error, I take it was this: they could not, or would not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt the figne, and the thing ſignified; betweene the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable aſſiſting preſence of God, and the outward and viſible
<pb facs="tcp:17808:8"/>token thereof. The Arke was there, and the Prieſts were there, and
<note n="a" place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> 
               <hi>wo vnto vs</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Philiſtims) God is come into the Hoſte;</hi> and yet the Lord was not there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Templum Domini, Templum Domini,</hi> the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, ſay the Iewes in the 7. of <hi>Ieremie</hi> the 4. verſe: This is the Temple of the Lord, as if all had beene well, and ſo ſure, that the Lord could not haue beene diſpleaſed with them, ſo long as the Temple ſtood among them. This Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of the Iewes, is falne vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily into the Iumpe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles and the
<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 11.17.21.</note> 
               <hi>wilde Oliue tree</hi> that is <hi>graft in,</hi> hath drunke of the vnſauorie licour of the <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall branches,</hi> that were <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:8"/>
            <p> It is good, that wee ſay, Lord, Lord, yet not
<note n="a" place="margin">Math. 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>euery one that ſaith Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> It may prooue a good beginning to confeſſe with the <hi>mouth,</hi> but
<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 10.9.</note> thou canſt not be ſaued, <hi>vnleſſe alſo thou beleeue with thy heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> in the preſence of <hi>Saul,</hi> calleth <hi>Goliah,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam. 17.36.</note> an <hi>vncircumciſed Philiſtin,</hi> and yet <hi>Sauls</hi> eſtate, was as wretched, and deſperate, though circumciſed; ſo true it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Galatians</hi> 6.15. <hi>neither circumciſion auaileth any thing, nor vncircumciſion, but a new creature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee haue the word of God, (as it were) the Arke of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, the Preachers alſo of this bleſſed word, <hi>the leuites</hi> and the Prieſts. We haue the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God,</hi> the Seales of this
<pb facs="tcp:17808:9"/>Couenant, and the Pleadges, of his reconciliation and peace, towardes vs; and yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all this, the Lord God may haue a controuerſie with vs, and wee may bee farre from peace.</p>
            <p>Thus haue we made inquiry, and thus haue we found it out, it is the doctrine of the ancient, euen of the
<note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ancient of daies,</hi> as <hi>Daniell</hi> ſpeaketh. Let vs weigh it well, and ſearch out the cauſes: for that (in a time of peace, when the precious word of GOD, and the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of GOD, which are the flagges (as it were) and Enſignes, of his loue and kindenes toward vs) that there ſhould be iarres (I ſay) and contentions, &amp; rumours of warres; this is ſtrange in deed, and it concerns vs very much to
<pb facs="tcp:17808:9"/>vnderſtand it. This Text aimes at this marke, &amp; will guide vs to this knowledge, let vs girde vp the loynes of our mindes, and take our ſtaues in our hands, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue her foote-ſteppes and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after her.</p>
            <q>There is no peace, ſaieth the Lord. &amp;c.</q>
            <p>This Prophet began to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, vnder the reigne of <hi>Vzzi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> or <hi>Azariah</hi> King of Iudah; who (as wee read in 2. Kings 15. cap. 5. verſe) was ſuddenly ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a leproſie, for vſurping the Prieſts office, He propheſied vnder foure Kings, ſo wee finde in the firſt Chapter of this booke and other Stories of the Church doe tell vs, that hee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnder the fift, not a naturall
<pb facs="tcp:17808:10"/>but a bitter, and violent death; being by the bloudy commaund of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> ſawne in ſunder, with a woodden Saw, after hee had propheſied, vnto the people of the Iewes,
<note n="g" place="margin">Vnder, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham, 16. and vnder Ahaz, 16. vnder He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiah, 29. theſe numbers make 61. how many yeares he propheſied vnder Azari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures tell vs not, of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours vnder Manaſſes they are vtterly ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</note> threeſcore years, and more. His birth was noble, the Sonne of <hi>Amos,</hi> Brother (as it is probale) of King <hi>Amazias,</hi> his eloquence admirable, in a high and loftie phraſe of ſpeech, as hee that can reade him in the originall may eaſily perceiue, and hence it is (ſaith <hi>Hierome</hi>)
<note n="t" place="margin">Prolog. in Iſaiam.</note> 
               <hi>vt prae caeteris florem ſermonis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, tranſlatio non potuerit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruare,</hi> that the tranſlation could not reteine the grace of the words of this Prophets diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p>There is not one, among the Prophets of the old Teſtament, that ſpeaketh ſo euidently, and
<pb facs="tcp:17808:10"/>pleinely, of the <hi>Moſstah,</hi> and his ſufferings, as this one doth, ſo that indeede (as the ſame father ſaith) <hi>Non tam Propheta dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſit, quam Euangeliſta,</hi> hee may rather bee named an Euangiliſt, then a Prophet: for hee (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundreth yeares before CHRISTS Incarnation) ſo clearely laied downe, the whole myſterie of Chriſt, and our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, <hi>vt non putes de futuro vaticinari, ſed de praeteritis hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam texere,</hi> that hee ſeemed, rather to haue publiſhed an hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory vnto the world, of things paſt, then to haue propheſied of things to come.</p>
            <p>The propheſies conteined in this booke, may (not vnfitly) bee diſtributed into theſe two kinds, <hi>legall</hi> and <hi>euangelicall;</hi> the <hi>legall</hi> propheſies are ſuch, as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb facs="tcp:17808:11"/>againſt the Iewes, or againſt the enemies of the Iews. Againſt the Iewes, many afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for their rebellion, &amp; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, bondage and captiuitie, vnder the Babilonians. Againſt the enemies of the Iewes, diſſipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and perpetuall deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Euangelicall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, conſiſt partlie of their deliuerie from that Babilonian captiuity, partly of the election, counſel, and gratious couenaunt of GOD, of the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of Chriſt, and his <hi>glory,</hi> of the <hi>prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>calling</hi> of the Gentiles.</p>
            <p>This verſe which I haue read vnto you, is part of a <hi>legal Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> denouncing a heauy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt al wicked perſons, as well Iewes, as Babilonians, and Gentiles, of what eſtate or
<pb facs="tcp:17808:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>condition ſoeuer. I will not ſtand, in many words to declare, the coherence of this verſe with the former. Breifly, thus much I will teach of that point. It is the concluſion of one entire Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of this Prophet, continued from the beginning of the 44. cap. hetherto; the generall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect whereof, is, the reuerſion or returne of the Iewes out of the captiuity of Babilon.</p>
            <p>Theſe words the Prophet vſeth, as a forcing argument to that purpoſe, namelie to perſwade the people to depart from thence with ſpeede: <hi>exite á Babilonia, fugite á Chaldaeis: goe out of Babell, flie from the Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> in the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie verſe of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>Nowe in as much as by that bodelie captiuitie, is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
<pb facs="tcp:17808:12"/>there ſpirituall ſeruitude, and bondage vnder ſinne; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet with their departure from that, would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, and principallie intimate their flight from this; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from ſinne, and from the companions, or rather ſlaues of ſinne.</p>
            <p>This the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in his 51. Chap. and 6. verſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth more plainely, <hi>Flee out of the middeſt of Babel, and deliuer euery man his ſoule, be not deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her iniquity.</hi> Thus much of the words, as they haue their dependance of the matter that goeth before: now wee wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of them abſolutely, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out relation, and as they are in themſelues.</p>
            <q>There is no peace. &amp;c.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> This Text hath the vertue, and full force of a Syllogiſme; for howſoeuer the parts of the Syllogiſme ſtand not here di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, yet are they neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily included, and the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that make for the deduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a ſound concluſion, out of the Premiſſes, plainely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. For the better expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this, you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the queſtion thus, <hi>An pax ſit impijs,</hi> whether the wicked haue peace; it is concluded in this Text, that they haue no peace, the <hi>medium concludendi,</hi> or proofe of this, is an argument <hi>à diuino teſtimonio,</hi> that is, from the witneſſe or teſtimonie of Gods owne mouth: the Lord hath ſpoken it, therefore the wicked haue no peace; there is no peace, ſaith the Lord vnto
<pb facs="tcp:17808:13"/>the wicked. Yee ſee then that this concluſion is negatiue, the extreames whereof are two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall contraries, and therefore cannot poſſiblie be affirmed one of another but denied. For as white cannot bee affirmed of blackneſſe, nor light of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, no more can true peace, of ſinne and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>The argument drawne from the diuine teſtimonie, is vſed here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, by way of pre-ocupation, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, and it argueth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie of the heart of man, in this point, and his groſſe and beaſtly errour. As if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had thus ſayd; How ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer the wicked and carnall men of this world, becauſe they liue in proſperitie, and haue of all things in aboundance, ſuffering
<pb facs="tcp:17808:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>no outward affliction, nor miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, doe conceit themſelues to bee ſeated in a kinde of perfect peace, and therefore can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bee drawne to entertaine an other doctrine, and to beleeue a contrary aſſertion: yet the Lord God of Heauen and Earth, who is wiſdome it ſelfe, hee knoweth it, and who is truth it ſelfe, hee hath pronounced it, that they haue no peace: and therefore how be-it, they flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with outwarde ſhewes and ſhaddowes, yet in trueth they haue no part of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>there is no true peace vnto them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sinne is an ill Maiſter that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his ſeruants no reſt, an euill, and ingratefull Gueſt, who the more hee is welcomed, and the better enterteinment
<pb facs="tcp:17808:14"/>hee hath, the more hee vexeth and diſquieteth his Hoſt: ſo that as <hi>Eliah</hi> ſayd vnto <hi>Achab.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1. Kin. 18.18</note> 
               <hi>It is thou that troublest Iſrael;</hi> ſo may euery man reply vpon his ſinne, it is thou that troubleſt me: oh that I had peace in my ſoule! but alas thou wilt not ſuffer mee. Wicked men haue no peace, not becauſe they are men, for ſo the Lord cheriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, and fauoureth them, but becauſe they are wicked men, and this is a maine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that the Spirit of God lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth downe in this Text, why there can bee no peace vnto the wicked.</p>
            <p>There is nothing but ſinne that maketh a man vnhappie; for there is nothing that ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateth man from his God, but ſinne, and if man becauſe of
<pb facs="tcp:17808:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſinne, bee ſeperated from his GOD, the GOD and Prince of peace: how can there then bee peace vnto that man? Man in the day of his innocencie, had a two-fould peace, ſaieth <hi>Bernard: Vt nec intus pugnae, nec foris timores,</hi> hee had neither ſtrife within, nor feares with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. The <hi>Fleſh</hi> offered not to lay his foule hands vppon the <hi>Spirit,</hi> thence aroſe his inward peace, and hence (partly) was his peace with GOD, and from this peace, ſprange that outward, euen peace with all the creatures of GOD. But ſo ſoone as the Diuell had cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted him, and that hee had ſubſcribed, with hand, and heart vnto rebellion; hee loſt his peace with the creatures, and hidde himſelfe from GOD.
<pb facs="tcp:17808:15"/>
               <note place="margin">ſ Gen. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>I heard thy voyce in the Garden, and was afraide,</hi> KI GNEIROM ANOKI, becauſe I was naked. The garment of righteouſneſſe, the robe of his former integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and holyneſſe, was pluckt from his backe, and now there was nothing to bee ſeene, but a naked man, wounded with ſinne, and infected with the leproſie of iniquitie: no maruell then though hee were afraide, <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta miſer timeo</hi> (ſaieth the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et) <hi>quia feci multa proterué,</hi> I feare much, becauſe I offend much: where ſinne goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there feare followeth, and where this feare hath gotte the place, there is no roome for peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caine,</hi> after hee had bath'd his hands in his brothers bloud, and that he felt himſelfe ſpoiled
<pb facs="tcp:17808:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the peace that hee had with God: hee was poſſeſſed, (and not without iuſt cauſe) with an exceeding feare, leaſt the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures alſo, ſhould make warre againſt him. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>thou hast cast mee out this daye, from the face of the earth, and from thy face ſhall I hide my ſelfe, and I ſhall bee a vagabonde and a wanderer in the earth, and ſo it ſhall come to paſſe, that euery one that findeth mee, ſhall kill mee.</hi> In what a woefull taking was this wretched man after his ſinne? how were his thoughts troubled and perplexed: Hee had neither <hi>pacem pectoris,</hi> nor <hi>pace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> corporis,</hi> neither peace with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in himſelfe, nor peace without himſelfe. <hi>I ſhal be hid from thy face</hi> (ſaith he) there hee was robbed of his inward peace, his peace
<pb facs="tcp:17808:16"/>with God: <hi>And euery one that findeth mee will kill mee,</hi> here was hee left naked of that out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace, that hee had with the creatures of God.</p>
            <p>Shall I need to laye before your eyes, a multitude of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples? Had <hi>Saul</hi> peace? had <hi>Achab</hi> peace? what peace had <hi>Iefabell</hi> more then <hi>Zimri?</hi> had <hi>Iudas</hi> peace? nay let euery <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horam</hi> inquire of his <hi>Iehu,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2. King. 9.22</note> 
               <hi>Is it peace Iehu?</hi> is it peace? and it ſhall anſwere him, <hi>What peace?</hi> what ſpeakeſt thou of peace? ſo long as <hi>the fornications of thy mother Iezabel,</hi> the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of thine owne wicked and rebellious heart, bee in ſo great a number?</p>
            <p>It is well worthy our beſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, that may bee gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of the wordes in the
<pb facs="tcp:17808:16"/>
               <hi>Original.</hi> The word <hi>Shalom,</hi> that ſignifieth peace,
<note place="margin">Heb.</note> commeth of the Verbe <hi>Shalah,</hi> which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>quieſcere,</hi> or <hi>quietum eſſe,</hi> to bee calme, ſtill, or to bee at reſt. But the word that is here tranſlated, the <hi>wicked, Reſhagnim,</hi> is deriued of <hi>Raſhang,</hi> which hath a contrarie ſignification, <hi>inquietum eſse,</hi> or <hi>tumultuari,</hi> to bee troubled and toſſed vp and downe, like the water, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted. This is the right tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and condition of the wicked man: his ſinnes are like the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering windes, that cauſe the billowes of his breſt, ſo violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to rage and ſwell, that hee can haue no peace at all; and hence it is, that this our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in his 57. chapter, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth him vnto the raging Sea, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>20</label> 
               <hi>that is beaten too and fro, and
<pb facs="tcp:17808:17"/>taketh no rest, but caſteth vp mire and dirt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let vs heare the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> obiect: <hi>The wicked proſper, and increaſe in riches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.5.12.</note> 
               <hi>they are not in trouble as other men.</hi> Let vs ioyne the holy <hi>Iob</hi> complaining with him, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iob. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>the earth is giuen into the hand of the wicked.</hi> And now what ſhall we anſwer vnto theſe mightie witneſſes? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer with the ſaying of <hi>Bernard</hi> vpon <hi>Caine; conſolatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſeram, obtinent, quam quaerunt,</hi> they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the miſerable comfort which they deſire, but that true conſolation and peace, which (aboue all things) is to bee deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, they ſhall neuer obtaine.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Caine</hi> had loſt his peace with God; he beſought him, that hee might haue, at the leaſt, an outward peace; that hee might
<pb facs="tcp:17808:17"/>not bee forced to flee from place to place, as a vagabond to ſaue his life. The Lord gaue him a protection for his life, and gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him licence to poſſeſſe the earth. In like manner, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlye men of the world, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing loſt that <hi>pacem aeternita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> peace which abideth for euer, they neuertheleſſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine at the hands of God, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cario,</hi> by way of entreatie, <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem temporis,</hi> (as <hi>Hugo Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis</hi> ſpeaketh) that is to ſay, temporarie and externall peace, and an aboundance of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye things, more many times then their hearts doe. But alas, ſmall comfort can they reape out of theſe things, the end of which is bitterneſſe:
<note n="b" place="margin">Prou. 24.1.</note> 
               <hi>The heart of the wicked</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon) euen in laughter ſorroweth,
<pb facs="tcp:17808:18"/>and the end of his myrth is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is well worthy your moſt Chriſtian attention, which the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> debateth in the beginning of his 12. chapter. <hi>O Lord</hi> (quoth hee) <hi>if I diſpute with thee, thou art righteous, yet let mee talke with thee of thy iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper? why are they at</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">So the word Shalu ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</note> 
               <hi>peace that rebelliouſlie tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe? why haſt thou planted them? and why doe they take roote? why doe they growe and bring forth fruite?</hi> Marke how the Prophet himſelfe reſolueth this queſtion namely, <hi>that thou mayest pull them out like the beasts for the ſlaughter, and prepare them for the day of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi> What ioy is there in this proſperitie? what comfort can there be in ſuch a peace, that
<pb facs="tcp:17808:18"/>ruine, and deſtruction attendeth vpon?</p>
            <p>What ioy had <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhatzer,</hi> in the plentifull and royall Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet, that hee made vnto his thouſand Princes? when in the midſt of his cups, hee beheld a hand, writing the ſentence of his preſent downefall? <hi>His thoughts were troubled</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>his ioynts were looſed and his knees ſmote one againſt another.</hi> His companie could not comfort him, nor the varietie of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, no nor the remembrance that hee was a King, ouer many kingdomes and Prouinces, could eaſe his thoughts, or bring any peace vnto him.</p>
            <p>Take all the moſt pleaſant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licates, that the Earth, the Seas, and the ayre may afford: let the wit and arte of man worke vpon
<pb facs="tcp:17808:19"/>them, and make them as anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable vnto the taſte, as the heart of man can wiſh. Set them (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with all the delights, that may giue ſatisfaction to the reſt of the ſenſes) ſet them I ſay before a man drawne out of the dungion to execution; and bid him fall to, and eate his fill, and bee merry. Will he glut himſelfe thinkeſt thou? will hee feed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy dainties? no doubtleſſe, hee will put his knife vnto his throate, and refraine his appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. And hee will anſwer thee, I can take no delight in theſe things, becauſe I perceiue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie times are growing vpon me, and death and diſſolution wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth for mee.</p>
            <p>Euen thus it is with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man: although his barnes be full, and his preſſes ouer-flow,
<pb facs="tcp:17808:19"/>though hee haue Mines of gold, and riuers of Oyle; though hee number his Oxen by thouſands, and his Sheepe by tenne thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands: though hee bee as roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie arayed as <hi>Salomon,</hi> and fare as deliciouſlie as the riche Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: though hee want no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward meanes, that may adde one iotte of ioye and delight, to rauiſh the heart of a carnall and ſenſuall man. How-ſo-euer hee may ſeeme for a time, to laugh and reioyce, and to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet himſelfe with the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of theſe things: yet if his heart bee communed withall, and examined vppon the point, it will anſwer; I finde no peace in this aboundance: they are but as Viniger powred vpon <hi>Nitre,</hi> and as Songs vnto a heauie heart, I take no pleaſure in
<pb facs="tcp:17808:20"/>them; for why I ſee alwayes before my face, the fingers of a hand, writing bitter things againſt mee. When all theſe things haue their end, as they cannot long continue, when the vn-wel-come and woefull time commeth, wherein they will forſake mee, or that I muſt bee taken awaye from them: there can (I ſee,) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nothing vnto mee, but a fearfull expectation of wrath, and the declaration of the iuſt iudgmentes of the Almightie GOD, againſt mee for my ſinnes.</p>
            <p>This is the force of an euill conſcience, which as the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Orator could ſay; is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie great indeede;
<note place="margin">Cicero, pro Milone.</note> 
               <hi>vt paenam ſemper ante oculos verſari pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, qui ſunt rei magnorum ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerum,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17808:20"/>in as much, as they that are guilty of heynous offences, thinke their puniſhments to bee euer-more before their faces: therefore they ſpake to good purpoſe, that called the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of men, <hi>fraenum et flagrum,</hi> a Bitte, and a Whip. A Bitte or Bridle that checketh the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man, admoniſheth him of the fouleneſſe of his ſinne, and pulleth him backward, that hee ruſh not head-long into it. A whippe, that ſcourgeth, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth him, when hee hath committed it.</p>
            <p>Let the Godleſſe Epicures of the world, deride, and make a mock, of all the teſtimonies of Gods prouidence; yet this one argument deriued from the griefe and horror of conſcience, it is, ſo reall, ſo euident, ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,
<pb facs="tcp:17808:21"/>that they ſhall neuer auoide it, nor delude it. Let <hi>Dionyſius</hi> make a mocke of all religion, yet this ſhall make him to trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and quake. This ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright <hi>Caligula</hi> in his ſleepe by night, and perſue him with dreadfull apparitions by daie. The force of this ſhall make <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> to ſtabbe himſelfe, and <hi>Iudas</hi> to hang himſelfe. In a word where this conſcience is, it will prooue it ſelfe (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) <hi>Iudicem et vltorem ſceleris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 7. et 44.</note> a Iudge, and a reuenger of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. It will not ſuffer the wicked heart, to bee at reſt and peace, but will follow him, from place to place with open out-cries, with proclamations of warres, and deadly hoſtility.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that the wiſeman ſaith of the wicked, that hee
<pb facs="tcp:17808:21"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>flyeth when no man perſueth him:</hi> no there needes not the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of man, when his owne conſcience taketh vp armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. He ſhall feare, with the
<note n="b" place="margin">2 King. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>Aramits,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 53.5.</note> 
               <hi>where no feare is</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh). A noiſe (as it were) of horſes and a ruſhing of Chariots ſhalbe in his eares: <hi>trepidabit ad arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis vmbram,</hi> the ſhaddow of a Reede ſhall diſmay him, yea as it is in <hi>Leuiticus,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Leuit. 26.36.</note> 
               <hi>the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of a leafe ſhall chaſe him, and hee ſhall flee, as if hee fled from the ſword.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.</note> Hee ſhall ſay in the morning, oh that it were euening, and againe at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, oh that it were morning, for the feare of his heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee ſhall feare, and for the ſight of his eyes, which hee ſhall ſee.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:22"/>
            <p> Thus the ſcriptures deſcribe the turbulent eſtate of a wicked and ſinfull man.</p>
            <p>What tho the ſtranger ſhall wiſh thee peace, in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when thou goeſt forth? and thy neighbours, and friends ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute thee with peace? and tho at thy returne, thy familie ſhall pray for thy peace? what if in the Church thou heare the word of peace? and receiueſt the Sacraments, which are the ſignes of peace? yet if thy heart luſt after ſinne, if it bee voide of Religion, and ſpoiled of the grace of God; if thou haue made a couenant with vanity, and ſmitten hands with iniquitie, thou knowſt, thou haſt no peace; for thou haſt a witneſſe within thy breſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will not lie (<hi>oh te mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerum</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca) ſi hunc con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnis
<pb facs="tcp:17808:22"/>teſtem,</hi> miſerable and wretched art thou, if thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne this witneſſe) thy gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and barking conſcience, that ſhall tell thee, <hi>there is no peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a right worthie and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent conceipt of him,
<note place="margin">Bucholcer.</note> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled this conſcience a <hi>practical Syllogiſme,</hi> the <hi>Maiar</hi> propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof is the law of God; the <hi>Minor</hi> and the concluſion, the application of the <hi>Theſis ad hypotheſin,</hi> that is to ſay, of that law, vnto a mans owne particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſon, approuing good and condemning euill. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> in his conſcience reaſoned thus: <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatours and adulterers God will iudge, for it is written thou ſhalt not commit adulterie,</hi> there's the law, and that makes the <hi>Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But I am an Adulterer;
<pb facs="tcp:17808:23"/>therefore GOD will iudge mee:</hi> here's the application of that law vnto his owne perſon, and that makes vppe the reſt of the Syllogiſme. But thou wilt ſay, if this bee ſo, and if this kinde of reaſoning which no man is freed from, bee the cauſe of horrour and diſquietneſſe of minde, What peace can there bee to any man liuing? ſeeing euery man is ſinfull? and what peace, could <hi>Dauid</hi> haue in heart, more then <hi>Caine</hi> or <hi>Iudas?</hi> if his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience concluded ſuch bitter things againſt him.</p>
            <p>I anſwere with that of <hi>Paul</hi> Col. 2.14. that the <hi>hand writing of ordinances, that is contrarie vnto vs,</hi> (which is the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an euill conſcience) <hi>Chriſt Ieſus hath taken it out of the waie, and faſtened it vpon his Croſſe.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17808:23"/>The lawe therefore remaineth ſtill, <hi>for CHRIST</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Math. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>came not to deſtroie the law, but to fulfill it.</hi> And it ſerueth to the humbling of mans ſoule, that hee may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his inſufficiencie, while hee compareth his owne weakeneſſe, and imperfection, with the ſtrength &amp; perfection which the law requireth: but that <hi>Chirographum,</hi> or hand wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, that indenteth iudgements, &amp; puniſhments, againſt the ſons of men, which I call <hi>the particular application of an euill conſcience,</hi> the precious bloud of Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, hath defaced it and blotted it out.</p>
            <p>So that the lawe may ſay, <hi>Hee that ſinneth ſhall die the death,</hi> yea and the deare Childe of GOD, may aſſume, and anſwere, in the ſorrow of his
<pb facs="tcp:17808:24"/>heart; <hi>it is I that greeuiouſly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe and ſinne;</hi> and yet the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, ſhall not make againſt him, for his conſcience ſhall propheſie vnto him, as <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid: the Lord hath taken away thy ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence it is that the Princely Prophet in the 32. Pſalme, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth that man bleſſed whoſe iniquitie is forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes are couered.
<note place="margin">Ber. lib. de conſcientia.</note> 
               <hi>Non dixit</hi> (ſayth <hi>Bernard) quorum nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae inuentae ſunt, ſed quorum remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae ſunt iniquitates; non quorum nulla ſunt, ſed quorum tecta ſunt peccata:</hi> the Prophet did not pronounce thoſe bleſſed, in whom there is no iniquity fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but thoſe, whoſe iniquities are remitted, not thoſe who haue no ſinne (for then our ſtate were deſperate) but thoſe whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:17808:24"/>ſinnes are couered.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I framed (as brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as I might) a Bodie of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine out of this Text: Your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience I beſeech, vntill I breath life into it, and then Ile com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to the grace of God, who is onely able to make it liuely vnto your ſoules.</p>
            <p>Art thou cruſhed vnder the burthen of a troubled and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing conſcience? and art thou afraide that the peace of GOD is taken from thee, for the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy ſinnes? what wilt thou now doe? where wilt thou inquire for comfort, where wilt thou inquire for reſt? <hi>grandis tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatio, vbi nullus euadendi locus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorie,</hi> it is a very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, and grieuous tribulation, from whence there is no way to eſcape, where there is no likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood
<pb facs="tcp:17808:25"/>of libertie, no hope of deliuerie. If thou returne to theſe outward helps, and ſeekeſt peace in earthly, and tranſitorie things: behold there, afflictions will preſſe thee downe, cares will torment thee, a multitude of miſeries will gaze vpon thee, and circumuent thee. For what true conſolation lyes there, in the pleaſures of this life? and what is the ioy that ariſeth out of riches? ſhall they abide with vs for euer? will they not take their wings and begone?
<note place="margin">Math. 13.22.</note> are they not the thornes that choake the word of God in vs,
<note place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16.</note> which the Lord hath appointed to bee the ſweete ſauour of life vnto life, to all that ſhall bee ſaued? breed they not more ſorrowe in their loſſe, then ioy in their
<pb facs="tcp:17808:25"/>poſſeſſion? what then remaines but this? flee to CHRIST IESVS, the <hi>Fountaiue of peace,</hi> the <hi>GOD of peace,</hi> the <hi>Prince of peace.</hi> Laye hold vpon him with the arme of a liuely faith: let him not depart from thee, vntill hee haue bleſſed thee, vntill hee ſaye vnto thy poore diſtreſſed ſoule, <hi>I am thy ſaluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe; Is this peace ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a thing? a peace that paſſeth all vnderſtanding? Is it a iewell of ſo pretious and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie vſe? that without it, the aboundance of the riches, and of the delights of this world, are turned vnto vs, into gall and bitterneſſe? and hath that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Oracle pronounced; that this peace falls not to the lotte
<pb facs="tcp:17808:26"/>of wicked men, and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their wickedneſſe? what remaineth then, but that wee make warre with our ſinnes, that wee may haue peace with GOD? Hee that hath peace with his ſinnes, the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth open warre againſt him; that this warre therefore may bee turned into a happie peace, let vs make warre with our ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Craeſus</hi> beeing taken captiue of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> vſed this one reaſon to preferre peace before warre, namely, becauſe in the time of <hi>Peace,</hi> the children might bury their Parents, but in <hi>Warre,</hi> the Parents (with much heauineſſe) buryed their children. But in this ſpirituall batteling, wee may vſe the ſame argument, to
<pb facs="tcp:17808:26"/>preferre <hi>warre</hi> before <hi>peace:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in <hi>peace</hi> our children and wicked off-ſpring, (that is) our ſinnes, bury vs; whereas if wee make warre againſt them, wee burie them.</p>
            <p>I know, I know, the Diuell will perſwade vs, to play with our ſinnes: but in the meane while, wee may bee ſuch that they will not play with vs, but as the yong-men played before <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Ioab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 2.14.10.</note> to take the life of our ſoules from vs. They will ſay, as <hi>Iael</hi> vnto <hi>Siſera,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudges. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Turne into vs, and feare not:</hi> they <hi>will prouide Milke</hi> for vs: they will deuiſe meanes to couer vs, and to lull vs <hi>a ſleepe,</hi> but the end of all this will prooue a deadly ſtroake. They will come vnto vs as the craftie <hi>Gibeoniſts</hi> vnto
<note place="margin">Ioſuab. 9.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:17808:27"/>
               <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>11</label> with deceitfull prouiſion, and ſay, <hi>wee wilbe your ſeruants, come and make a league with vs:</hi> but wee muſt prouide a means, to keepe them in ſubiection,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Verſe. </seg>21</label> and make them <hi>Hewers of wood,</hi> and <hi>Drawers of water,</hi> at the leaſt, or rather becauſe wee are not ty'de to keepe our othes and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants with ſinnes, let vs take them, and their children by the heeles, and daſh out their braines againſt the ſtones.
<note place="margin">Exo</note>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Moyſes</hi> had not ſlaine that impure <hi>Egyptian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">d. 2.</note> the poore <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe,</hi> had had no reſt. If thoſe fiue wicked Nations had not beene deſtroied, before the Iewes had ſeated themſelues, in the Land of Canaan, where had beene their peace? <hi>Saul</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored
<pb facs="tcp:17808:27"/>
               <hi>Agag,</hi> but it was with the loſſe of his kingdome. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore the caſe is ſo dangerous: let <hi>Agag</hi> bee ſlaine, yea let <hi>Achan</hi> bee ſlaine expell the <hi>Canaanits,</hi> kill the <hi>Epyptian.</hi> Let vs ſlaie our luſts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, mortifie our fleſh, reſiſt the diuell, deſtroie the wickedneſſe of our gain-ſaying, and rebellious hearts. Oh how bleſſed ſhall wee bee, if wee doe thus? doubtleſſe wee ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe our ſoules in peace, whiles we liue, and end our daies in the ioy of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The portion of time, that is cut out for vs, in this world is but <hi>ſhort,</hi> and <hi>vncertaine;</hi> And what a follie is it then, to liue in ſuch a ſort, in which wee dare not die?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17808:28"/>
            <p> The houſe wherein our ſoules dwell,
<note place="margin">Eceleſi. 12.</note> threatneth our ruine, on euery ſide. The
<note n="a" place="margin">Hands.</note> keepers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do tremble, and the
<note n="b" place="margin">Legges.</note> ſtronge men bowe themſelues: the
<note n="c" place="margin">Teeth.</note> Grinders ceaſe, becauſe they are few, and the windowes of the eyes grow dimme; ſeeing therefore, it cannot long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, but fall it will, and muſt; let vs bee carefull, to prouide for our ſelues, an other houſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the houſe of a quiet, and good conſcience.</p>
            <p>Our bodie is but as a Tent or Tabernacle, which muſt bee pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 51.</note> heere and there, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued from place, to place, in the war-fare of this life: but our conſcience, is our houſe and palace, in which, (when the troubleſome war-fare of this
<pb facs="tcp:17808:28"/>life, is at an end) wee muſt take our reſt;
<note place="margin">Ber de interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ori Domo.</note> therefore hee warreth well indeed (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) that ſo fighteth in his body againſt ſinne, that hee alſo, build vp an houſe of <hi>peace,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, for his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Thus haue I drawne, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented my waters vnto you, and if you deſire to drinke of any, beſides thoſe of the Well of <hi>Beth-lehem,</hi> I hope you will taſte of theſe alſo. I compare not the droppes of my ſmaller Springs, with the ſtreames of thoſe profound and Chriſtall Fountaines of <hi>Bethel;</hi> queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, they are drawne with great labour and paines,
<note place="margin">2 Sam. 23.16.</note> and many times with the ieopardie of their deareſt liues, for which cauſe perhaps, yee powre them
<pb facs="tcp:17808:29"/>(with <hi>Dauid</hi>) vpon the earth, and yee drinke them not. Theſe are none ſuch, therefore they deſire (though they deſerue worſe) a better entertainement. Courſer fare, amongſt your dainty delicates, ſometimes may gette a welcome: and groſſer meate may prooue profitable, now and then, at leaſt thus farre, <hi>vt cum pro faſtidio ſumitur</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregorie) ad ſubtiliores epulas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidiùs redeatur;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gre. in prefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione in Hom. ſuper Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clem.</note> that when you haue fedde on them vntill you loath, you may returne with a better appetite to the dainties you loue. The Lord in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie grant, that our ſoules may ſtill bee fedde with the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome bread of the ſimple and ſauing word of God, not made ſowre with the leauen of mans
<pb facs="tcp:17808:29"/>witte (an offering not to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the Lord) but ſeaſoned and ſweetned with the bleſſing of his ſanctifying Spirit,
<note place="margin">Leuit. 2.11.</note> that it may become a ſauoure of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life vnto euery one of our ſoules, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake; to whome with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons, but one onely God, let praiſes be giuen by Angels, and by men, and by all his creatures in heauen and in earth, for euermore.</p>
            <p>Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
